Guide to the Paul L. Holmer Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Course-related material, n.d.; Series III
  - Wittgenstein - Philosophical Issues in Theology: "Meaning" and Wittgenstein (course); Syllabus, Study Questions, notes; "Wittgenstein's Notes on Freedom of the Will" [notes taken by Y. Smythes of a lecture on Freedom of the Will. c. 1945-46]; Class roster for North Park Theological Seminary [c. 1995] -- Wittgenstein and Christian Understanding; notes; Article, 1945-1946, 1995 (Box 34, Folder 636)
  - Wittgenstein - Bibliography: Works by Wittgenstein (1889-1951); Syllabus: "Philosophical Issues in Theology: 'Meaning' and Wittgenstein; An Outline of a Course of Lectures on Logic; Two letters regarding the Ahlstrom library at Gustavus Adolphus College; Program for AAR/SBL Southeastern Region, March 16-18, 1978 (Box 34, Folder 637)
  - Wittgenstein - Philosophical Investigations; photocopy of "Philosophical Investigations" entry in Masterpieces of World Philosophy; study questions for Philosophical Investigations, Culture and Value, Tractatus; hand-written notes and outlines (Box 34, Folder 638)
  - Wittgenstein and Kierkegaard - syllabus for Philosophical Issues in Theology: 'Meaning' and Wittgenstein; syllabus for Phil. 200 Wittgenstein and Kierkegaard; Estheticism/The Esthetic (Box 34, Folder 639)
- Correspondence, Series IV
  - Letter to Prof. W. E. Hocking [of Cambridge, MA] - unsigned, 1936 (Box 35, Folder 640)
  - Letters to PLH from H. Richard Niebuhr, Dhirendra Mohan Datta, Wilmon H. Sheldon, Krister Stendahl, "Gene". Letter from PLH to Joseph Kitagawa, "Clarence", 1954 (Box 35, Folder 641)
  - Letters to PLH from Paul Leo [of Wartburg Theological Seminary], "Perry", Preston Warren, J. Edward Dirks, "Ralph", Harley K. Hallgren, Bishop Odd Hagen, E.V. Walter, Roger Ortmayer, 1955 Jan - Jul (Box 35, Folder 642)
  - Letters to PLH from Edith Runyan, Richard B. Burtis, Shirley Brekke, Donald L. Conrad, Bernie Loomer, Donald W. Wheat, Forrest Oran Wiggins, "Bernie", Franklin Sherman, Eliseo Vivas, Ernest D. Nielsen, Harold Bernhard, "J.B", Olaf Hansen, Al Martin, Niels Thulstrup, George L. Anderson, Seymour Cain, Howard Johnson, Robert M Herhold, Paul Jensen, Arnold E. Carlson. Letters from PHL to Bernard Ramm, Emerson W. Shideler, Sherman Bohn, Henry Gustafson, Shirley Brekke, Edith Runyan, Donald W. Week, 1955 Sep (Box 35, Folder 643)
  - Letters to PLH from Arthur Cochrane, Richard G. Schmitt, Ernest D. Nielsen, Richard Starr, Henry Albert Anderson, Carroll L. Hinderlie. Letters from PHL to Edvard von Krusenstierna, Albert Anderson, Carroll L. Hinderlie, Richard G. Schmitt, Henry Ehlers, Richard Starr, Ernest B. Nielsen, P.F.C. Lowell Nissen, Willem F. Zuurdeeg, 1955 Nov-Dec (Box 35, Folder 645)
  - Letters to PLH from Douglas V. Steere, Randolph C. Miller, 1957, 1964 (Box 35, Folder 646)
  - PLH to "Charlie", re: "responding belatedly to your comments about S. K.'s 'logically contradictory Christianity' ...", 1964 Dec (Box 35, Folder 647)
  - Letters to PLH from D. Allen, H. L. Short [of Manchester College, Oxford], Masao Abe, James F. Zartman, Howard Hong, Sidney A. Rand. Letters of PHL to Sidney A. Rand, Howard Hong; Letters to/fr John Linnell, Beverly Stadum, Albert G. Swanson, Howard and Edna Hong, 1966-1967 Mar (Box 35, Folder 648)
  - Letters to PLH from Marvin Repinski, James R. Lyons, Parker Rossman, James W. Dye, Rubin Gotesky, Edwin A. Schick, to/from J. Knudsen, Walter G. Emge, William G. Rusch, Richard J. Kelley, from James E. Dahlgren, 1967 May-1968 (Box 35, Folder 649)
  - Alan Gewirth [Program Committee for the American Philosophical Association] to PLH, 1971 (Box 35, Folder 650)
  - Letters to/from Robert L. Perkins, Donald K. McClelland, Cornelius Zylstra. Letters from PLH to Bart Collopy, S. J., Donald N. Eckerstrom, Carl F. H. Henry, Leo Jordan, Paul Kennedy, John Neumaier, Bernard Ruffin, 1972 (Box 35, Folder 651)
  - Letters to/from C. Stephen Evans, 1975 (Box 35, Folder 652)
  - PLH to Cornelius Zylstra. to/from Donald Macleod, to Wayne R. Whitelock, from Rachel M. Davies (Fortress Press), James I. McCord. Enclosures: Princeton Theological Seminary Baccalaureate - May 30, 1976; Princeton Seminary Baccalaureate program - May 29, 1977; "Making Sense Christianly" notes February 2, 1977, 1977 Feb-May (Box 35, Folder 653)
  - Letters from Gary R. Ahlskog, from Sidney A. Rand, 1977 Nov-Dec (Box 35, Folder 654)
  - Letters to/from Clifford Christians [Issue Editor of Communication ]. Letters to PLH from Rev. Margaret M. Kahin [of Ring Lake Ranch], Joseph H. Smith, Gary R. Ahlskog, 1978 (Box 35, Folder 655)
  - Letters to/from Joseph H. Smith (enc. letter from Michael Theunissen to Joseph H. Smith), Paul Christianson, Irene Snow, Edmund Leites, Richard John Neuhaus, "George", Clint Newton, David A. Hart,, Rob Lively, Harry B. Adams, Mark R. Branson, E. V. Walter, Margaret M. Kahin, Paul L. Redditt, David J. Wren, H. Edward Everding, Jr., Mike Frank, Donna M. Jacobs, Bob E. Patterson, 1979 (Box 35, Folder 656)
  - Letters to PLH from "Nellie", Charles E. Hummel, Noyuri Ohtsuka, Richard J. Dolven, Jean Lamo, Robert M. Goldstein, J. David Humbert, "Gib", Paul G. Kuntz, Katherine Ramsland, Richard Voyle. Letters to/from Peter Schneider, Fred J. Blum, Lois Dant, 1980-1983 (Box 35, Folder 657)
  - Letters to PLH from "Philip", Bob Goldstein, Gary R. Ahlskog, Alastair McKinnon, "G ... [?] McDaniel", Richard O. Johnson, Henri J. M. Nouwen to "Friends", Marilyn S. Breckenridge [Church of the Good Shepherd], Orloue Gisselquist [Augsburg College], Richard Rehfeldt [Windsor Heights Lutheran Church], Leif Knutsen, D. Z. Phillips, Ruth Moran, Michael Haeuser. Letters to/from Julian Hartt, David H. Sandstrom, George Abbott White, Ruth D. Fuller, Sherman E. Johnson [Dean, Church Divinity School of the Pacific], C. Stephen Evans, "Bud", " Gregg and Chris", "Martin and Erin", 1984-1986 (Box 35, Folder 658)
  - Letters to PLH from Philip J. Anderson, Chris Preus, Mary Severson, Brian O'Connor, Ned Wisnefske, "Suzanne", Leif Knutsen, D. Z. Phillips, Ruth Moran, Michael Haeuser, Dave Wold, Dennis Ormseth, Curtis Peter, Nancy L. Dahl, "Richard", Philip N. Stenberg, "Ron", Jim Christenson, Bernard Ramm, Daniel Carrigan, Mary Catherine Dean, Dabney Hart, Abraham Koh, Jeffrey Johnson, "Mila", David Fagerberg, Jerry Robbins, Charles J. Sykes, Wendell R. Debner, Joan L. Griffen, Rudolph L. Nelson, Steve Neumeister, Paul T. Dahlstrom, Heath K. Rada, 1987-1989 (Box 35, Folder 659)
  - Letters to PLH from "Bill", Heath K. Rada, Jeri Nelsen, Robert F. Thompson, Lachlan Reed, Brevard Childs, Harry Adams, Larry Goodwin, Michael Linton, Todd A. Driskill, Michael Lotti, Donald Meisel, Robert Pearson, Richard Rollefson, Ward K. Hahn, Orval Westby, Jeff and Kirsten Johnson, Stephen Schofield, Robert L. Perkins, Norman Wirzba, Abraham Koh, 1990-1991 (Box 35, Folder 660)
  - Letters to PLH from Carolyn Stickney Beck, John Poling, Paul H. Almquist, Michael Linton, Andy Byers, 1993-1995 (Box 35, Folder 661)
  - Letters to PLH from "Bill", re. William Cahoy reference, 1996-1997 (Box 35, Folder 662)
  - Letters to PLH from David Cain, Tom Hungerford, M. Frank [of the C. S. Lewis Society], Julian N. Hartt, Urban Forell, John Poling, Paul Dahlstrom, Thomas Greenspon, "Art", n.d. (Box 35, Folder 663)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series V
  - Documentation of activities
    - Programs, class record book, list of speaking engagements, 1955-1967 (Box 35, Folder 664)
    - Lutheran Church in America, Division for Professional Leadership, Consulting Committee on Theological Education, 1976 (Box 35, Folder 665)
    - "Bibliography of the Writings of Paul L. Holmer, 1943-1976," by E. Dale Madren, with notes, corres., 1977-1986 (Box 35, Folder 666)
    - Bulletin from service, list of speaking engagements, material re. presentation of Douglas Macintosh portrait at YDS; list of publications, lectures by PLH 1979-1980, 1978-1980 (Box 36, Folder 667)
    - Bulletins for wedding, speaking engagements, with notes, list of speaking engagements, info. re. teaching appointment at Augsburg College, 1981-1988 (Box 36, Folder 668)
    - Material re. "Minnesota Authors" series taught by PLH, 1990-1996 (Box 36, Folder 669)
    - Event and conference programs, notices, 1990-1996 (Box 36, Folder 670)
    - Bibliography of Holmer's writings prepared by David Gouwens, 2004 (Box 36, Folder 671)
  - Writings about Holmer
    - Newspaper articles: "Filosofiprossor I Minnesota Efterlyser en Hedeniusdebatt" by Erland Sundstrom with abbreviated English translation;"Theologian Pooh-Poohs Need for Historical Insight on Bible" in Kitchener-Waterloo Record (Nov. 9, 1963); "Yale Professor to Talk at 'U'" in The Minneapolis Star (Oct. 29, 1966), 1955,1963,1966 (Box 36, Folder 672)
    - "Learning How to be Religious: The Work of Paul Holmer," by Patrick Sherry in Theology, 81-90 (Feb. 1974) (Box 36, Folder 673)
    - "Contemporary Theology and Paul Holmer" by Cornel West; "The Grammar of Faith: The Philosophical and Moral Philosophy of Paul L. Holmer" - Dissertation proposal by Richard Rollefson (Box 36, Folder 674)
    - "Holmer's Audience" - retirement tribute by YDS professor [?], ca. 1987 (Box 36, Folder 675)
    - "Paul Holmer: a Profle" by Mark Horst, Christian Century, p. 891-895, 1988 Oct 12 (Box 36, Folder 676)
    - Obituary from Yale Bulletin and Calendar; tributes to Holmer, including by Arvid Adell, Bruce Carlson, Paul L. Holmer, Jr, Richard John Neuhaus, William H. Willimon, 2004 (Box 36, Folder 676)
- Collected Material, Series V
  - Writings by others
    - Anderson, Philip: "David F. Swenson, Evolution, and Public Education in Minnesota" (Box 36, Folder 677)
    - Bell, Richard H.: "NEH Fellowship for College Teachers - Description of Proposed Study", n.d. (Box 36, Folder 677)
    - Dahlstrom, Paul: "Thoughts While Starving", n.d. (Box 36, Folder 677)
    - Eidmann, Philipp Karl: "The Doctrine of Consciousness Only as Formulated in Vasubandhu's Vigesimal and Trigesimal", ca. 1951 (Box 36, Folder 678)
    - Erling, Bernhard: "The Contemporary Critique of Christocentric Ethics in Scandinavia", 1976 (Box 36, Folder 678)
    - Feigl, Herbert: four papers, 1958, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 679)
    - Flew, Antony: "On Speaking Infallibly", n.d. (Box 36, Folder 680)
    - Garrard, L.A.: "The Death of God", n.d. (Box 36, Folder 680)
    - Hamann, Johann Georg: "Socratic Memorabilia", n.d. (Box 36, Folder 681)
    - Holmer, Linnea: "Durkheim and Wittgenstein: Some Logical Questions about the Notion 'Elementary Forms of Life'", 1969 (Box 36, Folder 682)
    - Hong, Howard and Edna: "Joy and Hope Walk the Earth" (Box 36, Folder 683)
    - Jensen, A. Dewey: "Moral Value: Disjecta Membra ", n.d. (Box 36, Folder 684)
    - Jones, Joe R.: "Some Remarks on Authority and Revelation in Kierkegaard" (Box 36, Folder 684)
    - Jorgensen, Carl: "Soren Kierkegaard's Disappointment" - trans. by Lene Carpenter, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 685)
    - Kierkegaard, Soren: "What We Learn from the Wild Lilies and the Birds of the Air" - Part Two of Edifying Discourses in Various Spirits - bound typescript translation presented to PLH by Howard and Edna Hong; "What Does it Mean to Doubt?" (Box 37, Folder 686)
    - Kierkegaard, Soren: Edifying Discourses, Volumes 1-4 - Holmer's annotated copies, 1943-1946 (Box 39, Folder 706)
    - Moeckel, F. W.: Script / poetry "Sirren Churchyard", n.d. (Box 37, Folder 687)
    - Newton, Clint: Fiction fragments, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 688)
    - Nielsen, H.A.:"The Concept of Sin Consciousness", n.d. (Box 37, Folder 688)
    - Poling, John: "Chapel Talk", 2000 (Box 37, Folder 688)
    - Ramm, Bernard: "An Annotated Bibliography of the History of Theology from Schleiermacher till 1951"; "The Incipient Heresies of Soren Kierkegaard", 1952, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 689)
    - Schrag, Calvin: "The Phenomenon of Embodied Speech", n.d. (Box 37, Folder 690)
    - Swenson, David F.: "Analytical Outline of and Quotations from the Marriage Essay in Either-Or, Volume II" (Box 37, Folder 691)
    - Thomte, Reidar: "The Structure of the Human Synthesis: A study in Kierkegaard's Concept of the Self", 1963 (Box 37, Folder 692)
    - Thulstrup, Niels: "An Introduction to Kierkegaard's Philosophical Fragments " - trans. by Howard Hong, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 692)
    - Walden, Ron: "Biblical Studies in the Theological Curriculum", 1973 (Box 37, Folder 693)
    - Westphal, Merold:"Kierkegaard as Prophetic Philosopher", 1976 (Box 37, Folder 693)
    - Wittgenstein, Ludwig: "Lecture on Ethics"; "Remarks on Frazer's The Golden Bough ", 1967, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 694)
    - Set of mimeographed papers on theological/philosophical topics by Alston, Hick, McKinnon, Machle, Nielsen, Paul, Penelhum, Phillips, Stenson, van der Ziel, Zucker (Box 37, Folder 695)
    - Miscellaneous student papers by Kwiatek, Langworthy, Moore, Plows, Poling, Radcliffe, Rambo, Roberts, Rogness, Saltzman, Wilson (Box 37, Folder 696, 697)
    - Unidentified: "Concept of Grammar", n.d. (Box 19, Folder 238)
    - Unidentified: "Kierkegaard" 54 pp typescript (Box 20, Folder 259)
    - Unidentified: "Is Religion a 'Form of Life'?", n.d. (Box 20, Folder 258)
    - Unidentified: "On the Quality of Theological Education", n.d. (Box 21, Folder 277)
  - Topical material
    - Intention and literature: photocopies from books and articles (Box 38, Folder 698)
    - Kierkegaard: Photographs taken in Copenhagen by Joel Olsen, incl. of Kierkegaard gravesite, Kierkegaard Room in City Museum, SK statue in park, etc., 1974 (Box 38, Folder 699)
    - Kierkegaard: Index to references to scripture in the translated works of Kierkegaard by Paul S. Minear and Paul S. Morimoto; Index of entries in SK's Papirer; Bibliographies of works by and about SK, 1949, 1966, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 700)
    - Kierkegaard: Misc. re. statue, SK Society, Times Literary Supplement article, SK genealogy, 1948-1969,n.d. (Box 38, Folder 701)
    - Lewis, C.S.: Incl. bibliography of CSL works, paper written by CSL for World Council of Churches Assembly Commission II: "Modern Man and His Categories of Thought", 1946, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 702)
    - Minnesota: Facsimile copy of Lake Minnetonka Tourist Vol.1 No. 5, 1876 (Box 38, Folder 703)
    - Tolstoy: NY Times and National Geographic articles about Tolstoy, 1986, 1994 (Box 38, Folder 704)
    - Wittgenstein: Bibliography of LW works; oral history proposal; biographical material, 1949-1989 (Box 38, Folder 705)